<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>software engineering on James Akl</title><link>https://jamesakl.com/tags/software-engineering/</link><description>Recent content in software engineering on James Akl</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jamesakl.com/tags/software-engineering/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Premature intervention</title><link>https://jamesakl.com/posts/premature-intervention/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jamesakl.com/posts/premature-intervention/</guid><description>In systems and software, premature intervention can be harmful. The term “premature optimization” represents a broader concern than is often understood. Usually, this involves making critical changes or wasting efforts before system parameters are understood (requirements, constraints, trade-offs, …) thereby adding complexity and reducing adaptability.
Instances of premature intervention include: (but are not limited to)
Premature abstraction (≈ introducing abstractions before behavior stabilizes, obscuring intent and increasing indirection) Premature modularization (≈ imposing module boundaries before cohesion and coupling are evident, which can restrict flexibility) Premature implementation (≈ committing to code before key programming decisions are settled, resulting in rework) Premature architecting (≈ applying patterns or frameworks before goals and constraints are clear, adding rigidity) Premature scaling (≈ designing for performance, scale, or concurrency beyond foreseeable need, wasting effort) Premature optimization (≈ optimizing code without profiling or identifying bottlenecks, which can reduce clarity) Premature generalization (≈ engineering for speculative use cases that are imagined without basis, increasing complexity without payoff) Premature tooling (≈ building automation or infrastructure before workflows stabilize, risking misalignment) Intervention is good and timely when grounded by strong reasons.</description></item></channel></rss>