<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on James Akl</title><link>https://jamesakl.com/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on James Akl</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jamesakl.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Principled testing</title><link>https://jamesakl.com/posts/principled-testing/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jamesakl.com/posts/principled-testing/</guid><description>Testing software-intensive systems involves more decisions than the standard vocabulary suggests. The conventional taxonomy (unit, integration, system, acceptance) organizes tests along a single axis of scope. But each test also involves deciding why to run it (intent), where to run it (environment), and how to judge correctness (the oracle: the mechanism that decides whether an output is right). Separating these decisions can clarify what a test strategy covers and where the gaps are.</description></item><item><title>Proof clarity</title><link>https://jamesakl.com/posts/proof-clarity/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jamesakl.com/posts/proof-clarity/</guid><description>Mathematical proofs can be difficult to read—even for the person who wrote them. Some of this difficulty is intrinsic: abstract structures, nested quantifiers, long dependency chains. But some is incidental, arising not from the logical content but from choices in exposition. Proofs tend to be compressed, and less often refactored for comprehension.
The interpretive burden Disciplines that manage complex information tend to develop organizational systems. Accounting has double-entry bookkeeping, standardized ledgers, and audit trails.</description></item><item><title>CUDA ontology</title><link>https://jamesakl.com/posts/cuda-ontology/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jamesakl.com/posts/cuda-ontology/</guid><description>CUDA&amp;rsquo;s terminology carries significant overloading: the word &amp;ldquo;CUDA&amp;rdquo; itself refers to at least five distinct concepts, &amp;ldquo;driver&amp;rdquo; means different things in different contexts, and version numbers reported by various tools measure different subsystems. This article provides a rigorous ontology of CUDA components: a systematic description of what exists in the CUDA ecosystem, how components relate to each other, their versioning semantics, compatibility rules, and failure modes. Each term is defined precisely to eliminate ambiguity.</description></item><item><title>Distribution anti-patterns</title><link>https://jamesakl.com/posts/distribution-antipatterns/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jamesakl.com/posts/distribution-antipatterns/</guid><description>Two common distribution problems emerge in robotics systems: distributing computation and distributing communication.
ROS 2 (robotics middleware built on DDS for message passing and more) is purpose-built for the communication problem — coordinating messages between robots, drivers, and software components across network boundaries. It is sometimes applied to the computation problem — parallelizing work inside a single system or process.
In prototyping, this approach can accelerate development. In more mature deployments, however, it can produce architectures where too many processing steps exist as separate nodes.</description></item><item><title>Research progress</title><link>https://jamesakl.com/posts/research-progress/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jamesakl.com/posts/research-progress/</guid><description>Often, when researchers disagree about what topics or approaches to prioritize, they are also disagreeing on what kinds of progress are more important. This stems from implicit preferences in research goals and aesthetics. One researcher might dismiss a theoretical model as impractical, while another sees a prototype as ephemeral.
These tensions reflect deeper contrasts in how progress is interpreted and pursued. ‘Progress’ can&amp;rsquo;t be decomposed cleanly, but it can still be probed through contrastive axes.</description></item><item><title>Premature intervention</title><link>https://jamesakl.com/posts/premature-intervention/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jamesakl.com/posts/premature-intervention/</guid><description>In systems and software, premature intervention can be harmful. The term “premature optimization” represents a broader concern than is often understood. Usually, this involves making critical changes or wasting efforts before system parameters are understood (requirements, constraints, trade-offs, …) thereby adding complexity and reducing adaptability.
Instances of premature intervention include: (but are not limited to)
Premature abstraction (≈ introducing abstractions before behavior stabilizes, obscuring intent and increasing indirection) Premature modularization (≈ imposing module boundaries before cohesion and coupling are evident, which can restrict flexibility) Premature implementation (≈ committing to code before key programming decisions are settled, resulting in rework) Premature architecting (≈ applying patterns or frameworks before goals and constraints are clear, adding rigidity) Premature scaling (≈ designing for performance, scale, or concurrency beyond foreseeable need, wasting effort) Premature optimization (≈ optimizing code without profiling or identifying bottlenecks, which can reduce clarity) Premature generalization (≈ engineering for speculative use cases that are imagined without basis, increasing complexity without payoff) Premature tooling (≈ building automation or infrastructure before workflows stabilize, risking misalignment) Intervention is good and timely when grounded by strong reasons.</description></item></channel></rss>